So the machine I'm going to talk you about
حسنا، الآلة التي سأحدثكم عنها
is what I call the greatest machine that never was.
هي ما أدعوه بأعظم آلة في التاريخ.
It was a machine that was never built,
إنها آلة لم يتم قط بناؤها،
and yet, it will be built.
ومع ذلك، سيتم بناؤها.
It was a machine that was designed
لقد كانت آلة تم تصميمها
long before anyone thought about computers.
لفترة طويلة قبل أن يفكر أحد في الحواسيب.
If you know anything about the history of computers,
إن كنتم تعرفون أي شيء عن تاريخ الحواسيب،
you will know that in the '30s and the '40s,
ستعرفون أنه في الثلاثينيات والأربعينيات
simple computers were created
تم إنشاء الحواسيب البسيطة
that started the computer revolution we have today,
التي بدأت ثورة الحواسيب التي نراها اليوم،
and you would be correct,
وستكونون محقين،
except for you'd have the wrong century.
باستثناء أنه ستكونون قد فكرتم في القرن الخاطئ.
The first computer was really designed
أول حاسوب قد تم تصميمه فعلا
in the 1830s and 1840s, not the 1930s and 1940s.
في ثلاثينيات وأربعينيات القرن التاسع عشر، وليس في القرن الماضي.
It was designed, and parts of it were prototyped,
لقد تم تصميمه، وتمت نمذجة أجزاء منه،
and the bits of it that were built are here
وقطعه التي تمت صناعتها موجودة هنا
in South Kensington.
في جنوب كنسينغتون.
That machine was built by this guy, Charles Babbage.
تلك الآلة بناها هذا الرجل، تشارلز باباج.
Now, I have a great affinity for Charles Babbage
الآن، لدي وجه شبه عظيم مع تشارلز باباج
because his hair is always completely unkempt like this
لأن شعره يكون دائما أشعت هكذا
in every single picture. (Laughter)
في كل صورة. (ضحك)
He was a very wealthy man, and a sort of,
لقد كان رجلا فاحش الثراء، ونوعا ما،
part of the aristocracy of Britain,
جزء من الطبقة الأرستقراطية في بريطانيا،
and on a Saturday night in Marylebone,
وفي ليلة يوم أحد في ماريليبون،
were you part of the intelligentsia of that period,
وإن كنت جزء من النخبة المثقفة في تلك الحقبة،
you would have been invited round to his house
ستتم دعوتك لهذا المنزل
for a soiree — and he invited everybody:
لأمسية — وقد دعا الجميع:
kings, the Duke of Wellington, many, many famous people —
الملوك، دوق ولينغتون والعديد من المشاهير —
and he would have shown you one of his mechanical machines.
وقد يعرض عليك أحد آلاته الميكانيكية.
I really miss that era, you know, where you could
أحن حقا إلى تلك الحقبة، تعرفون، حيث يمكنكم
go around for a soiree and see a mechanical computer
التوجه إلى أمسية ورؤية الحاسوب الميكانيكي
get demonstrated to you. (Laughter)
يعرض عليك. (ضحك)
But Babbage, Babbage himself was born
لكن باباج، باباج نفسه قد ولد
at the end of the 18th century,
في نهاية القرن الثامن عشر،
and was a fairly famous mathematician.
وقد كان عالم رياضيات مشهورا.
He held the post that Newton held at Cambridge,
وقد كان يشغل منصبا كان نيوتن قد شغله في كامبردج،
and that was recently held by Stephen Hawking.
والذي قد شغله مؤخرا ستيفن هوكينغ.
He's less well known than either of them because
وهو أقل شهرة من أي منهما لأنه
he got this idea to make mechanical computing devices
جاء بفكرة صناعة أجهزة حوسبة ميكانيكية
and never made any of them.
ولم يصنع أيا منها.
The reason he never made any of them, he's a classic nerd.
والسبب الذي منعه من صناعة أي منها، هو أنه مهووس قراءة كلاسيكي.
Every time he had a good idea, he'd think,
في كل مرة تخطر بباله فكرة جيدة، فهو يفكر،
"That's brilliant, I'm going to start building that one.
"ذلك أمر رائع، سأقوم ببدء بناء تلك.
I'll spend a fortune on it. I've got a better idea.
سأصرف عليها ثروة. لدي فكرة أفضل.
I'm going to work on this one. (Laughter) And I'm going to do this one."
سأشتغل على هذه الفكرة. (ضحك) وسأقوم بإنجاز هذه."
He did this until Sir Robert Peel, then Prime Minister,
وقد دأب على القيام بذلك إلى أن قام السير روبرت بيل، رئيس الوزراء آنذاك،
basically kicked him out of Number 10 Downing Street,
بطرده من عنوان رقم 10 شارع داونينغ،
and kicking him out, in those days, that meant saying,
وطرده آنذاك كان يعني قول،
"I bid you good day, sir." (Laughter)
"طاب يومك سيدي." (ضحك)
The thing he designed was this monstrosity here,
ما قام بتصميمه كان هذه الآلة الضخمة هنا،
the analytical engine. Now, just to give you an idea of this,
المحرك التحليلي. الآن، فقط لإعطائكم فكرة حول هذا،
this is a view from above.
هذه نظرة علوية.
Every one of these circles is a cog, a stack of cogs,
كل واحدة من هذه الدوائر هي مسننة، حزمة من المسننات،
and this thing is as big as a steam locomotive.
وهذا الشيء بقدر ضخامة قاطرة بخار.
So as I go through this talk, I want you to imagine
لذا، وأنا أمضي في هذه المحادثة، أريد منكم أن تتخيلوا
this gigantic machine. We heard those wonderful sounds
هذه الآلة الضخمة. لقد سمعنا تلك الأصوات المذهلة
of what this thing would have sounded like.
للأصوات التي كانت لتصدر عن هذه الآلة.
And I'm going to take you through the architecture of the machine
وسأقوم بأخذكم حول معمارية الآلة
— that's why it's computer architecture —
— لذلك تمت تسميتها معمارية الحاسوب —
and tell you about this machine, which is a computer.
وأخبركم حول هذه الآلة، والتي هي حاسوب.
So let's talk about the memory. The memory
لذا، دعونا نتحدث عن الذاكرة. الذاكرة
is very like the memory of a computer today,
هي مثل ذاكرة الحاسوب اليوم،
except it was all made out of metal,
باستثناء أنها كانت مصنوعة كليا من المعدن،
stacks and stacks of cogs, 30 cogs high.
أكوام وأكوام من المسننات، بعلو 30 مسننة.
Imagine a thing this high of cogs,
تخيلوا شيء بهذا العلو من المسننات،
hundreds and hundreds of them,
مئات ومئات منها،
and they've got numbers on them.
كتبت عليها أرقام.
It's a decimal machine. Everything's done in decimal.
إنها آلة عشرية. كل شيء يتم بنظام عشري.
And he thought about using binary. The problem
وقد فكر في استخدام النظام الثنائي. المشكل
with using binary is that the machine would have been so
في استخدام النظام الثنائي هو أن الآلة كانت لتكون فارعة
tall, it would have been ridiculous. As it is, it's enormous.
الطول، كانت لتبدو سخيفة. وهي بتلك الضخامة.
So he's got memory.
وبالتالي فهي تتوفر على ذاكرة.
The memory is this bit over here.
والذاكرة هي تلك القطعة هناك.
You see it all like this.
تراها كلها هكذا.
This monstrosity over here is the CPU, the chip, if you like.
هذه البشاعة هنا هي المعالج، الرقاقة، إن شئتم.
Of course, it's this big.
وبالطبع هي بهذا الحجم.
Completely mechanical. This whole machine is mechanical.
ميكانيكية بالكامل. الآلة بأكملها ميكانيكية.
This is a picture of a prototype for part of the CPU
هذه صورة لنموذج أولي لجزء من المعالج
which is in the Science Museum.
الموجود في متحف العلوم.
The CPU could do the four fundamental functions of arithmetic --
ويستطيع المعالج إجراء العمليات الحسابية الأربعة الأساسية --
so addition, multiplication, subtraction, division --
أي الجمع والضرب والطرح والقسمة --
which already is a bit of a feat in metal,
والتي في حد ذاتها تعتبر إنجازا في المعدن،
but it could also do something that a computer does
لكنها تستطيع كذلك القيام بشيء يقوم به الحاسوب
and a calculator doesn't:
ولا تستطيعه الآلة الحاسبة:
this machine could look at its own internal memory and make a decision.
هذه الآلة تستطيع النظر داخل ذاكرتها الداخلية وتتخذ قرارا.
It could do the "if then" for basic programmers,
تستطيع تنفيذ أمر "إذا كان .. فإن" للمبرمجين الأساسيين،
and that fundamentally made it into a computer.
وهذا جعلها أساسا حاسوبا.
It could compute. It couldn't just calculate. It could do more.
تستطيع الحوسبة. لا تستطيع فقط الحساب. تستطيع القيام بأكثر من ذلك.
Now, if we look at this, and we stop for a minute,
الآن إن نظرنا إلى هذا، وتوقفنا لدقيقة،
and we think about chips today, we can't
وفكرنا في الرقائق اليوم، لا نستطيع
look inside a silicon chip. It's just so tiny.
النظر داخل رقاقة سيليكون. فهي غاية في الدقة.
Yet if you did, you would see something
وحتى لو قمت بذلك، سترى شيء
very, very similar to this.
مشابها جدا لهذا.
There's this incredible complexity in the CPU,
هناك تعقيد مذهل في المعالج،
and this incredible regularity in the memory.
وهذا الانتظام المذهل في الذاكرة.
If you've ever seen an electron microscope picture,
إذا نظرت إلى صورة بالمجهر الإلكتروني
you'll see this. This all looks the same,
سترون هذا. كل هذا يبدو متشابها،
then there's this bit over here which is incredibly complicated.
وبالتالي فهذه القطعة هنا معقدة بشكل لا يصدق.
All this cog wheel mechanism here is doing is what a computer does,
وآلية العجلة المسننة هذه بأكملها تقوم بما يقوم به الحاسوب،
but of course you need to program this thing, and of course,
لكن بالطبع ستحتاج لبرمجة هذا الشيء، وبالطبع،
Babbage used the technology of the day
قد استخدم باباج التكنولوجيا المتاحة
and the technology that would reappear in the '50s, '60s and '70s,
والتكنولوجيا التي ستعود للظهور في الخمسينيات والستينيات والسبعينيات،
which is punch cards. This thing over here
والتي هي البطاقات المثقبة. هذا الشيء هنا
is one of three punch card readers in here,
هو أحد ثلاث قارئات بطاقات مثقبة هنا،
and this is a program in the Science Museum, just
وهذا برنامج في متحف العلوم، غير
not far from here, created by Charles Babbage,
بعيد من هنا، أنشأه تشارلز باباج،
that is sitting there — you can go see it —
والذي يوجد هناك — يمكنكم الذهاب لرؤيته —
waiting for the machine to be built.
في انتظار بناء الآلة.
And there's not just one of these, there's many of them.
وليس هناك واحد منها فقط، هناك الكثير منها.
He prepared programs anticipating this would happen.
لقد قام بتحضير برامج متوقع حدوث هذا.
Now, the reason they used punch cards was that Jacquard,
الآن، السبب الذي جعلهم يستخدمون البطاقات المثقبة كان أن جاكارد،
in France, had created the Jacquard loom,
في فرنسا، قد أنشأ منسج جاكارد،
which was weaving these incredible patterns controlled by punch cards,
والذي كان ينسج هذه الأنماط المتحكم فيها باستخدام البطاقات المثقبة،
so he was just repurposing the technology of the day,
وبالتالي كان فقط يقوم بإعادة توظيف التكنولوجيا آنذاك،
and like everything else he did, he's using the technology
ومثل كل شيء آخر قام به، فهو يستخدم تكنولوجيا
of his era, so 1830s, 1840s, 1850s, cogs, steam,
حقبته، أي ثلاثينيات وأربعينيات وخمسينيات القرن 18، المسننات والبخار،
mechanical devices. Ironically, born the same year
أجهزة ميكانيكية. والتي، ومن سخرية الأمر، فقد ولد في نفس السنة
as Charles Babbage was Michael Faraday,
التي ولد فيها تشارلز باباج، مايكل فاراداي،
who would completely revolutionize everything
والذي سيحدث ثورة في كل شيء
with the dynamo, transformers, all these sorts of things.
بالمولد الكهربائي والمحولات وأشياء من هذا القبيل.
Babbage, of course, wanted to use proven technology,
لكن باباج، بالطبع، أراد استخدام تكنولوجيا موثوقة،
so steam and things.
أي البخار وما إلى ذلك.
Now, he needed accessories.
الآن، فقد احتاج إلى ملحقات.
Obviously, you've got a computer now.
وبالطبع، لديك حاسوب الآن.
You've got punch cards, a CPU and memory.
ولديك بطاقات مثقبة ومعالج وذاكرة.
You need accessories you're going to come with.
تحتاج إلى ملحقات تأتي بها.
You're not just going to have that,
لن تتوفر فقط على ذلك،
So, first of all, you had sound. You had a bell,
لذا، قبل كل شيء، كان لديك صوت. كان هناك جرس،
so if anything went wrong — (Laughter) —
لذا إن حصل أي خطأ — (ضحك) —
or the machine needed the attendant to come to it,
أو إن احتاجت الآلة إلى مجيء الخادم إليها،
there was a bell it could ring. (Laughter)
كان هناك جرس يمكن قرعه. (ضحك)
And there's actually an instruction on the punch card
وهناك في الواقع تعليمات على البطاقة المثقبة
which says "Ring the bell." So you can imagine this "Ting!"
تقل "اقرع الجرس." وبالتالي يمكنكم تخيل ذلك الصوت "تينغ!"
You know, just stop for a moment, imagine all those noises,
تعرفون، توقفوا للحظة فقط، وتخيلوا كل تلك الأصوات،
this thing, "Click, clack click click click,"
هذا الشيء، "كليك، كلاك كليك كليك كليك،"
steam engine, "Ding," right? (Laughter)
المحرك البخاري، "دينغ،" صحيح (ضحك)
You also need a printer, obviously, and everyone needs a printer.
تحتاج كذلك إلى طابعة، وبالتأكيد، يحتاج الجميع إلى طابعة.
This is actually a picture of the printing mechanism for
هذه في الواقع صورة لآلية الطباعة
another machine of his, called the Difference Engine No. 2,
لآلة أخرى له، تدعى محرك الفرق رقم 2،
which he never built, but which the Science Museum
والتي لم يقم قط ببنائها، لكن متحف العلوم
did build in the '80s and '90s.
بناها في الثمانينيات والتسعينيات،
It's completely mechanical, again, a printer.
وهي بدورها طابعة ميكانيكية بالكامل.
It prints just numbers, because he was obsessed with numbers,
تقوم فقط بطباعة الأرقام، لأنه كان مهووسا بالأرقام،
but it does print onto paper, and it even does word wrapping,
لكنها تطبع على الورق، وتقوم حتى بلف الكلمات،
so if you get to the end of the line, it goes around like that.
وبالتالي إن وصلتم إلى نهاية السطر، تلتف حوله هكذا.
You also need graphics, right?
تحتاج كذلك إلى رسومات، أليس كذلك؟
I mean, if you're going to do anything with graphics,
أقصد، إن كنتم ستقومون بأي شيء باستخدام الرسومات،
so he said, "Well, I need a plotter. I've got a big piece of paper
فقال، "حسنا، أحتاج إلى رسام . أحتاج إلى قطعة ورق كبيرة
and an ink pen and I'll make it plot."
وإلى قلم حبر وسأجعله يرسم."
So he designed a plotter as well,
فقام بتصميم الرسام كذلك،
and, you know, at that point, I think he got pretty much
وتعرفون، آنذاك قد حصل على
a pretty good machine.
آلة جيدة للغاية.
Along comes this woman, Ada Lovelace.
ثم جاءت هذه المرأة، أدا لافليس.
Now, imagine these soirees, all these great and good comes along.
الآن، تخيلوا هذه الأمسيات، كل هؤلاء العظام والخبراء يجتمعون.
This lady is the daughter of the mad, bad
هذه الآنسة هي ابنة المجنون والسيء السمعة
and dangerous-to-know Lord Byron,
والخطير معرفته: اللورد بايرون،
and her mother, being a bit worried that she might have
ووالدتها، كانت شيء ما قلقة من أنها قد تكون
inherited some of Lord Byron's madness and badness,
ورثت بعضا من جنون وسوء اللورد بايرون،
thought, "I know the solution: Mathematics is the solution.
ففكرت، "أعرف الحل: الرياضيات هي الحل.
We'll teach her mathematics. That'll calm her down."
سنعلمها الرياضيات. وذلك سيهدئ من روعها."
(Laughter) Because of course,
(ضحك) لأنه بالطبع،
there's never been a mathematician that's gone crazy,
لم يحصل قط أن أصيب عالم رياضيات بالجنون،
so, you know, that'll be fine. (Laughter)
وبالتالي، تعرفون، سيكون ذلك حسنا. (ضحك)
Everything'll be fine. So she's got this mathematical training,
سيكون كل شيء على ما يرام. فحصلت على التدريب في الرياضيات،
and she goes to one of these soirees with her mother,
وذهبت إلى إحدى هذه الأمسيات مع أمها،
and Charles Babbage, you know, gets out his machine.
فقام تشارلز باباج، كما تعرفون، بإخراج آلته.
The Duke of Wellington is there, you know,
ودوق ولينغتون موجود هناك، كما تعرفون،
get out the machine, obviously demonstrates it,
أخرج الآلة، وقام بالطبع بعرضها،
and she gets it. She's the only person in his lifetime, really,
فاستوعبت الأمر. وقد كانت الشخص الوحيد في حياته،
who said, "I understand what this does,
الذي قال، "أفهم ما يقوم به هذا،
and I understand the future of this machine."
وأدرك مستقبل هذه الآلة."
And we owe to her an enormous amount because we know
ونحن مدينون لها كثيرا لأننا نعرف
a lot about the machine that Babbage was intending to build
الكثير عن الآلة التي كان باباج ينوي بناءها
because of her.
بسببها.
Now, some people call her the first programmer.
الآن، بعض الناس يدعونها أول مبرمجة.
This is actually from one of -- the paper that she translated.
وهذا في الواقع مأخوذ من إحدى الوثائق التي ترجمتها.
This is a program written in a particular style.
هذا برنامج مكتوب بصيغة خاصة.
It's not, historically, totally accurate that she's the first programmer,
وتاريخيا، ليس دقيقا بالكامل أنها أول من برمج،
and actually, she did something more amazing.
وفي الواقع، لقد قامت بشيء أكثر إذهالا.
Rather than just being a programmer,
وبدل كونها مجرد مبرمجة،
she saw something that Babbage didn't.
فقد رأت شيء أغفله باباج.
Babbage was totally obsessed with mathematics.
باباج كان مهووسا بالكامل بالرياضيات.
He was building a machine to do mathematics,
لقد كان يبني آلة للقيام بالرياضيات،
and Lovelace said, "You could do more than mathematics
وقد قالت لوفلاس، "يمكنك القيام بأكثر من الرياضيات
on this machine." And just as you do,
باستخدام هذه الآلة." وتماما كما تفعلون،
everyone in this room already's got a computer on them
كل من يوجد هنا يحمل معه حاسوبا
right now, because they've got a phone.
الآن، لأنه لديهم هاتف.
If you go into that phone, every single thing in that phone
إن فتحتم ذلك الهاتف، كل شيء في ذلك الهاتف
or computer or any other computing device
أو الحاسوب أو أي جهاز حوسبة آخر
is mathematics. It's all numbers at the bottom.
هو رياضيات. كلها أرقام في العمق.
Whether it's video or text or music or voice, it's all numbers,
سواء كانت فيديو أو نصا أو موسيقى أو صوتا، هي كلها أرقام،
it's all, underlying it, mathematical functions happening,
هي كلها، تكمن وراءها دوال رياضية تحدث،
and Lovelace said, "Just because you're doing
وتقول لوفلاس، "فقط لأنك تقوم بإجراء
mathematical functions and symbols
دوال ورموز رياضياتية
doesn't mean these things can't represent
لا يعني أن تلك الأشياء لا تمثل
other things in the real world, such as music."
أشياء أخرى في العالم الحقيقي، كالموسيقى."
This was a huge leap, because Babbage is there saying,
هذه كانت قفزة هائلة، لأن باباج كان يقول،
"We could compute these amazing functions and print out
"نستطيع حوسبة هذه الدوال المذهلة وطباعة
tables of numbers and draw graphs," — (Laughter) —
جداول أرقام ورسم مبيانات،" — (ضحك) —
and Lovelace is there and she says, "Look,
ولوفلاس كانت تقول، "انظر،
this thing could even compose music if you
هذا الشيء يمكنه عزف الموسيقى إن
told it a representation of music numerically."
أخبرته بتمثيل رقمي للموسيقى."
So this is what I call Lovelace's Leap.
وهذا ما أدعوه بقفزة لولافلاس.
When you say she's a programmer, she did do some,
حين تقول أنها مبرمجة، فقد قامت ببعض ذلك،
but the real thing is to have said the future is going to be
لكن الأمر الحقيقي هو أنها قالت أن المستقبل سيكون
much, much more than this.
أكثر من هذا بكثير.
Now, a hundred years later, this guy comes along,
الآن، بعد مئة سنة، يأتي هذا الرجل،
Alan Turing, and in 1936, and invents the computer all over again.
آلان تورينج وفي سنة 1936 ويخترع الحاسوب من جديد.
Now, of course, Babbage's machine was entirely mechanical.
الآن، وبالطبع، آلة باباج كانت ميكانيكية بالكامل.
Turing's machine was entirely theoretical.
آلة تورينج كانت نظرية بالكامل.
Both of these guys were coming from a mathematical perspective,
كلا الرجلين كانوا يتحدثون من منظور رياضياتي،
but Turing told us something very important.
وقد أخبرنا تورينج بشيء مهم للغاية.
He laid down the mathematical foundations
وقد وضع الأساس الرياضياتي
for computer science, and said,
لعلوم الحاسوب، وقال،
"It doesn't matter how you make a computer."
"لا يهم كيف تصنع حاسوبا."
It doesn't matter if your computer's mechanical,
لا يهم إن كان حاسوبك ميكانيكيا،
like Babbage's was, or electronic, like computers are today,
مثل حاسوب باباج، أو إلكترونيا مثل الحواسيب اليوم،
or perhaps in the future, cells, or, again,
أو ربما في المستقبل، خليويا، أو مرة أخرى،
mechanical again, once we get into nanotechnology.
ميكانيكيا، بعد دخولنا إلى النانوتكنولوجيا.
We could go back to Babbage's machine
قد نعود إلى آلة باباج
and just make it tiny. All those things are computers.
فنقوم فقط بجعلها دقيقة. كل تلك الأشياء هي حواسيب.
There is in a sense a computing essence.
هناك إدراك، إدراك حاسوبي.
This is called the Church–Turing thesis.
وهذه تدعى بأطروحة تشيرج ـــ تورينج.
And so suddenly, you get this link where you say
وهكذا فجأة، تصل إلى هذا الرابط حين تقول
this thing Babbage had built really was a computer.
ما بناه باباج قد كان فعلا حاسوبا.
In fact, it was capable of doing everything we do today
في الواقع، كان قادرا على القيام بكل ما نقوم به اليوم
with computers, only really slowly. (Laughter)
بالحواسيب، فقط بشكل أبطأ بكثير. (ضحك)
To give you an idea of how slowly,
لإعطائكم فكرة عن مدى بطئه،
it had about 1k of memory.
لقد كان يتوفر على ذاكرة بسعة 1 كيلو.
It used punch cards, which were being fed in,
وقد استخدم بطاقات مثقبة، يتم تغذيته بها،
and it ran about 10,000 times slower the first ZX81.
وقد اشتغل بشكل أبطأ ب 10,000 مرة من أول ZX81.
It did have a RAM pack.
قد توفر على حزمة ذاكرة RAM.
You could add on a lot of extra memory if you wanted to.
يمكنك إضافة الكثير جدا من الذاكرة إن أردت ذلك.
(Laughter) So, where does that bring us today?
(ضحك) إذن، إلى أين أوصلنا ذلك اليوم؟
So there are plans.
هناك مخططات.
Over in Swindon, the Science Museum archives,
في سويندون في أرشيفات متحف العلوم،
there are hundreds of plans and thousands of pages
هناك المئات من المخططات والآلاف من الصفحات
of notes written by Charles Babbage about this analytical engine.
من الملاحظات المكتوبة من طرف تشارلز باباج حول هذا المحرك التحليلي.
One of those is a set of plans that we call Plan 28,
أحدها هو مجموعة من الخطط نسميه الخطة 28،
and that is also the name of a charity that I started
وهو كذلك إسم لهيئة خيرية أنشأتها
with Doron Swade, who was the curator of computing
مع دورون سواد، والذي كان القيم على الحوسبة
at the Science Museum, and also the person who drove
في متحف العلوم، ونفس الشخص الذي قاد
the project to build a difference engine,
مشروع بناء محرك الفرق،
and our plan is to build it.
ونحن نخطط لبنائه.
Here in South Kensington, we will build the analytical engine.
هنا في جنوب كنسينغتون، سنقوم ببناء المحرك التحليلي.
The project has a number of parts to it.
والمشروع مقسم إلى عدد من الأجزاء.
One was the scanning of Babbage's archive.
أحدها كان مسح أرشيف باباج.
That's been done. The second is now the study
وقد تم ذلك. الثاني الآن هو دراسة
of all of those plans to determine what to build.
كل تلك المخططات لتحديد ما سنبنيه.
The third part is a computer simulation of that machine,
والجزء الثالث هو محاكاة حاسوبية لتلك الآلة،
and the last part is to physically build it at the Science Museum.
والجزء الأخير هو بناؤه فعليا في المتحف العلمي.
When it's built, you'll finally be able to understand how a computer works,
حين سيبنى، ستستطيعون أخيرا فهم كيفية اشتغال الحاسوب،
because rather than having a tiny chip in front of you,
لأنه بدل التوفر على رقاقة دقيقة أمامكم،
you've got to look at this humongous thing and say, "Ah,
عليكم أن تنظروا إلى هذا الشكل المتجانس وتقولوا، "آه
I see the memory operating, I see the CPU operating,
أرى الذاكرة تشتغل، أرى المعالج يشتغل،
I hear it operating. I probably smell it operating." (Laughter)
أسمعه يشتغل. وربما أشمه وهو يشتغل." (ضحك)
But in between that we're going to do a simulation.
لكن خلال ذلك سنجري محاكاة.
Babbage himself wrote, he said,
باباج نفسه كتب يقول،
as soon as the analytical engine exists,
بمجرد وجود المحرك التحليلي،
it will surely guide the future course of science.
سيقوم بالتأكيد بتوجيه المسار المستقبلي للعلوم.
Of course, he never built it, because he was always fiddling
وبالطبع، فهو لم يبنه قط، لأنه كان دائما يعبث
with new plans, but when it did get built, of course,
بمخططات جديدة، لكن حين تم بناؤه، بالطبع،
in the 1940s, everything changed.
في الأربعينيات، تغير كل شيء.
Now, I'll just give you a little taste of what it looks like
الآن، سأعطيكم لمحة عما يبدو عليه
in motion with a video which shows
وهو يتحرك بفيديو يعرض
just one part of the CPU mechanism working.
جزء واحدا فقط من آلية المعالج تشتغل.
So this is just three sets of cogs,
وبالتالي فهذه فقط 3 مجموعات من المسننات،
and it's going to add. This is the adding mechanism
وستقوم بالجمع. هذه آلية الجمع
in action, so you imagine this gigantic machine.
وهي تعمل، وبالتالي تتخيل هذه الآلة الضخمة.
So, give me five years.
لذا، أعطوني خمس سنوات.
Before the 2030s happen, we'll have it.
قبل حلول 2030، سنحصل عليه.
Thank you very much. (Applause)
شكرا جزيلا لكم. (تصفيق)